rapidminer.com 2019-10-06

# Privacy Policy | RapidMiner

Hello, and thank you for your interest in RapidMiner Inc. and its affiliates (“RapidMiner”). This Privacy Policy (“Policy”) is meant to help you understand what information we collect, why we collect it, and how you can update, manage, and delete your information. If you have any questions about this Policy, send us a note at [privacy@rapidminer.com](mailto:privacy@rapidminer.com).

RapidMiner collects information from multiple sources, including various websites hosted by or affiliated with RapidMiner (each a “Website” and collectively, the “Websites”) and various software products and services offered by RapidMiner (the “Software”). The Websites and the Software are referred to collectively in this Policy as the “Offerings”.

This Policy provides you with information concerning our practices and procedures as they relate specifically to information we collect via any Offering that incorporates this Policy. By using such Offering, you are accepting the practices described in this Policy. We may occasionally update this Policy to reflect changes in our practices. When we post modifications to this Policy, we will revise the “Last Revised” date at the bottom of this web page. The modified Policy will be effective immediately upon posting on the Website. Your continued use of the Offering after the posting of the modified Policy constitutes your agreement to abide and be bound by it. If we make any material changes we will notify you by email (sent to the e-mail address specified in your account) or by means of a notice on this Website prior to the change becoming effective and we will update the effective date accordingly. We encourage you to periodically review this page for the latest information on our privacy practices. If you object to any modification, your sole recourse is to stop using the Offering.

We’ll ask for your consent before using your information for a purpose that isn’t covered in this Policy. You may, of course, decline to share certain Personal Information with RapidMiner, in which case RapidMiner may not be able to provide to you some of the features and functionality found on the Offerings.

## Information Collected by RapidMiner

RapidMiner collects information from multiple sources, including the various Offerings. Some of this information can be used to identify you or another identified or identifiable natural person or other data subject (“Personal Information”). Other information is aggregated, anonymized, or otherwise not immediately usable to identify you or another natural person or data subject (“Anonymous Information”).  Personal Information and Anonymous Information are collectively referred to as “Customer Information” in this Policy.

###  _What do RapidMiner Websites Store and Collect?_

We collect information about the apps, browsers, and devices you use to access our Websites and Offerings or open one of our HTML emails by using different types of technology, including “clear gifs” or “web beacons.” This “automatically collected” information may include Internet Protocol address (also known as “IP address”) or other device address or ID, web browser or device type, the web pages or sites that you visit just before or just after visiting a Website, the pages you view on a Website, and the dates and times that you visit the Websites.

####  _Cookies and Web Beacons_

We use small text files called cookies to improve the overall Website experience. A cookie is a piece of data stored on the user’s hard drive containing information about the user. Cookies generally do not permit us to personally identify you (except as provided below). We may also use clear GIFs (a.k.a. “Web beacons”) in HTML-based emails sent to our users to track which emails are opened by recipients.

This information is collected directly by the third party, and RapidMiner does not participate in that data transmission. Information collected by third parties in this manner is subject to that third party’s own data collection, use, and disclosure policies.

####  _Types of Cookies_

The Websites uses the following types of cookies.

##### Essential Cookies

Essential (or “Required”) cookies that are required for providing you with features or services that you have requested. Disabling these cookies may make certain features and services unavailable.

##### Functionality Cookies

Functional cookies are used to record your choices and settings regarding our Websites, maintain your preferences over time, and recognize you when you return to our Websites. These cookies help us to personalize our content for you, chat with you on the website, and show videos to you.

##### Performance and Analytics Cookies

Performance/Analytical cookies allow us to understand how visitors use our Websites by collecting information about the number of visitors to the Website, what pages visitors view on our Website and how long visitors are viewing pages on the Website. Performance and Analytical cookies also help us measure the performance of our advertising campaigns in order to help us improve our campaigns and the content for those who engage with our advertising.

##### Retargeting and Advertising Cookies

Retargeting and Advertising cookies collect data about your online activity and identify your interests so that we can provide advertising that we believe is relevant to you.

####  _Cookie Settings_

You can decide whether or not to accept cookies. One way you can do this is through your internet browser’s settings. Most browsers have an option for turning off the cookie feature, which will prevent your browser from accepting new cookies. You can also delete all cookies that are already on your computer. If you do this, however, you may have to manually adjust some preferences every time you visit a site and some Website functionality might not work.

####  _Fulfillment Data_

If you choose to use a Website to purchase goods or services, we collect and process fulfillment data, some of which may be Personal Information. These are required individual details for the establishment, content or alteration of a contract. Which details are required depend on the goods or services you are procuring. The essential details can be identified by the asterisk (*). This includes – depending on the good or service – your name and e-mail address, billing information, company name, tax ID, address and telephone number, user name and password.

###  _What does the RapidMiner Software Collect?_

The Software may, from time to time, collect usage statistics on your use of and interaction with the Software, in order to further improve your experience with and learning of the Software and RapidMiner’s other products and services. In particular, the collected information is used to improve the usability and effective operation of the Software. The collected usage statistics include statistics on the execution of operators, operators and settings in processes, the selection of actions and navigation between elements in the user interface of the RapidMiner Software.

## Why RapidMiner Collects Information

RapidMiner uses the information we collect for the following purposes:

###  _Maintain & Improve Our Offerings_

We use your information to ensure the Offerings are working as intended, such as tracking outages or troubleshooting issues that you report to us. For example, we continuously monitor our products to look for problems. And if we find something wrong with a specific feature, reviewing activity information collected before the problem started allows us to fix things more quickly.

And we use your information to make improvements to the Offerings – for example, to understand and analyze the usage trends of the Software to improve it and build better products. Or it may help us discover that it’s taking users too long to complete a certain task or that they have trouble finishing steps at all. We can then redesign that feature and improve the product for everyone.

###  _Develop New Offerings_

We use the information we collect in the Offerings to help us create new features and functionality.

###  _Provide Personalized Services_

We use the information we collect to customize the Software for you, including recommending specific next steps for you to take while using the product.

###  _Measure Performance_

We use data for analytics and measurement to understand how our Offerings are used. For example, we analyze data about your visits to our sites to do things like optimize website design, monitor and analyze the operation and effectiveness of the Website, and monitor aggregate site usage metrics such as total number of visitors and pages viewed. We use a variety of tools to do this, including Google Analytics. Google Analytics relies on first-party cookies, which means the cookies are set by RapidMiner. You can opt-out from Google Analytics by clicking [here](https://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout).

###  _Communicate with You_

We use information we collect, like your email address, to interact with you directly. For example, we may email you to let you know about upcoming changes or improvements to the Software; or regarding things you post on the  Offerings. And if you contact RapidMiner, we’ll keep a record of your request to help solve any issues you might be facing.

## Managing and Deleting Your Information

When you’re signed into your RapidMiner account, you can always review and update information by visiting your RapidMiner account profile.

### Removing Your Information

To delete all of your information, send an email to [privacy@rapidminer.com](mailto:privacy@rapidminer.com). Once we confirm your identity, we will immediately start the process of removing your data from the product and our systems. As with any deletion process, things like routine maintenance, unexpected outages, bugs, or failures in our protocols may cause delays in the processes and timeframes in connection with such removal.

There are other ways to control the information RapidMiner collects, including configuring your browser to indicate when RapidMiner has set a cookie in your browser. You can also configure your browser to block all cookies from a specific domain or all domains. But remember, as described above, the RapidMiner Offerings rely on cookies to function properly.

## Third Party Websites

The Offerings contain links to websites and services provided by third parties. Any Personal Information you provide on third party sites or services is provided directly to that third party and is subject to that third party’s policies governing privacy and security. We are not responsible for the content or privacy and security practices and policies of third party sites or services to which links are displayed on the Offerings. We encourage you to learn about third parties’ privacy and security policies before providing them with Personal Information.

## Protection of Minors

RapidMiner Offerings are not intended for minors. For that reason, RapidMiner does not knowingly collect or maintain Personal Information from persons under 16 years old, and no part of the RapidMiner Offerings are directed to persons under 16. IF YOU ARE UNDER 16 YEARS OF AGE, PLEASE DO NOT USE OR ACCESS THE RAPIDMINER OFFERINGS AT ANY TIME OR IN ANY MANNER.

## Sharing Your Information

### When You Share Your Information

Some of our Offerings let you share information with other people, and you have control over how you share. Any information that you voluntarily choose to include in an area of the Offerings accessible to other RapidMiner members, such as a public profile page or in a posting, will be available to other RapidMiner members who access that content.

Also, if you communicate directly with another RapidMiner member, any information that you voluntarily choose to include in such a communication with other RapidMiner members will be available to such other members. Once you make your information available in any of these ways, it could be collected and used by the recipients without restriction. We urge RapidMiner users to exercise common sense, prudence and good judgment about what information to make available to others through the RapidMiner Offerings.

### When RapidMiner Shares Your Information

We are not in the business of selling your information. We do, however, disclose your Personal Information in connection with developing and maintaining the RapidMiner Offerings. We share your Personal Information in the following cases:

#### With your consent

We’ll share Personal Information outside of RapidMiner when we have your consent. For example, if you give us permission to share your information with a partner of RapidMiner.

#### For external processing

We provide Personal Information to our affiliates and other trusted businesses or persons to process it for us, based on our instructions and in compliance with our Privacy Policy and any other appropriate confidentiality and security measures. For example, we use service providers to help us with customer support. These third parties may have access to or process your Personal Information as a result of performing the services they were engaged to perform.

#### To Affiliates

We may share your Personal Information with our Affiliates who perform services or functions for us and who may use your information for purposes similar to the purposes for which we collect such information. We require our Affiliates to comply with the terms of this Privacy Policy.  For purposes of the foregoing an “Affiliate” means any corporation, partnership or other entity now existing or hereafter organized that directly or indirectly controls, is controlled by or under common control with RapidMiner.

#### For legal reasons

We will share Personal Information outside of RapidMiner if we have a good-faith belief that access, use, preservation, or disclosure of the information is reasonably necessary to:

  * Meet any applicable law, regulation, legal process, or enforceable governmental request.
  * Detect, prevent, or otherwise address fraud, abuse, security, or technical issues.
  * Protect against harm to the rights, property or safety of RapidMiner, our users, or the public as required or permitted by law.
  * Protect the security or integrity of the RapidMiner Offerings and to protect or enforce third party rights.

If RapidMiner is involved in a merger, acquisition, or sale of assets, we’ll continue to ensure the confidentiality of your Personal Information and give affected users notice before Personal Information is transferred or becomes subject to a different privacy policy.

## Security

We maintain reasonable administrative, technical and physical safeguards to protect Personal Information from loss, misuse and unauthorized access, disclosure, alteration and destruction.

If you have found a vulnerability or would like to report a security incident, you may send an email to [privacy@rapidminer.com](mailto:privacy@rapidminer.com).If RapidMiner learns of a security breach, we will notify you in accordance with applicable law.

## Compliance & Cooperation with Regulators

We regularly review this Privacy Policy and make sure that we process your information in ways that comply with it.

### Data Transfers

Your information may be processed on servers located outside of the country where you live. Data protection laws vary among countries, with some providing more protection than others. Regardless of where your information is processed, we apply the same protections described in this policy. We transfer your Personal Information from the European Union to the United States in accordance with standard contractual clauses we entered into.

When we receive formal written complaints, we respond by contacting the person who made the complaint. We work with the appropriate regulatory authorities, including local data protection authorities, to resolve any complaints regarding the transfer of your data that we cannot resolve with you directly.

### EU Residents

If European Union (EU) data protection law applies to the processing of your information, you can exercise your right to request access to, update, remove, and restrict the processing of your information. You also have the right to object to the processing of your information or export your information to another service. Please email privacy@rapidminer.com to exercise these rights.

We process your information for the purposes described in this policy, based on the following legal grounds:

#### With your consent

We ask for your agreement to process your information for specific purposes like sending emails, and you have the right to withdraw your consent at any time.

#### When we’re pursuing legitimate interests

We process your information for our legitimate interests while applying appropriate safeguards that protect your privacy. This means that we process your information for things like:

  * Providing, maintaining, and improving RapidMiner Offerings to meet the needs of our users.
  * Developing new products and features that are useful for our users
  * Understanding how people use our RapidMiner Offerings to ensure and improve their performance
  * Customizing RapidMiner Offerings to provide you with a better user experience
  * Marketing to inform users about our RapidMiner Offerings
  * Providing advertising to make many of our RapidMiner Offerings freely available for users
  * Performing research that improves our RapidMiner Offerings for our users and benefits the public

#### When we’re providing a service

We process your data to provide a service you’ve asked for under a contract. For example, we process your information in connection with your licenses to the RapidMiner Offerings.

#### When we’re complying with legal obligations

We’ll process your data when we have a legal obligation to do so, for example, if we’re responding to legal process or an enforceable governmental request.

#### California Residents

California law permits individuals who provide RapidMiner with Personal Information and who are California residents to request certain information regarding our disclosure of Personal Information to third parties for their direct marketing purposes.  RapidMiner does not, at this time, disclose Personal Information to third parties for their direct marketing purposes. If RapidMiner changes this policy, we will update this provision and provide instructions on how you may make a request for details concerning such information.

## Changes and Updates to this Privacy Policy

These policies may be amended from time to time. Your continued use of any RapidMiner Offering that incorporates this Policy will signify your acceptance of such amendment.

## How to Contact Us

Please contact RapidMiner with any questions or comments about this Privacy Policy, your Personal Information, our use and disclosure practices, or your consent choices through at [privacy@rapidminer.com](mailto:privacy@rapidminer.com).

## Last Revised

This Privacy Notice was last updated on May 24, 2018.
